原视频名：China's Mars Rover Zhurong Has Completed Its Primary Mission, Reaches New Milestone
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/aSSs6FfBlgY
原视频发布日期：20210824
字幕翻译：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
It's been three months since China's Zhurong rover landed on Mars
中国的祝融号火星车着陆火星已经三个月了
and began the process of slowly returning images and other scientific data from the surface of Mars.
并开始从火星表面缓慢返回图像和其他科学数据
Now depending upon how you measure it China is the second country to successfully land on Mars
那么取决于你如何衡量它 中国是第二个成功着陆火星的国家
but some may argue it's third or the fourth.
但有些人可能认为它是第三或第四
The other qualifiers are the Soviet Union which landed Mars 3 before United States did
其他有资格的国家是苏联 其火星三号比美国更早着陆
but unfortunately Mars 3 never returned any data and broke down seconds after landing.
但不幸的是 火星三号从未传回任何数据 并且在着陆后几秒钟就坏了
And Britain actually landed Beagle 2.
而英国实际上着陆了小猎犬2号
However they lost contact with it immediately
然而 (在着陆后)他们立即与它失去了联系
and it was only years later that photographs from Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter showed that
几年后 火星勘测轨道器拍下的照片才显示出
it had in fact began unfurling its solar panels
它实际上已经开始展开其太阳能电池板
but had been unable to complete this in contact
但未能在着陆后完成这一工作
so those are the other two candidates for soft landing
那么这就是另外两个软着陆的候选者
but let's be clear this is vastly more successful
但我们要清楚 这次着陆远比之前的这些着陆成功
and I think they totally deserve the second place trophy here.
所以我认为他们完全应该获得第二名的奖杯
Now immediately after landing there weren't any photos available and it took them several days
那么 在着陆之后不久 没有任何照片 而且他们花了几天时间
because the rover on the surface had a direct uplink that had a bit rate of like 16 bit/s
因为火表上的着陆器(到地球的)直接上行链路带宽大约为16位/秒
and they weren't about to start uploading megabytes of images over that.
而他们并不打算开始使用这种方法上传(高达)兆字节(MB)大小的图像
They had to wait for the Tianwen spacecraft in orbit to shift into a orbit
他们不得不等待轨道上的天问号航天器(轨道器)转入(中继)轨道
which would pass over the landing sites like once every day.
也就是每天都会从着陆点上空经过一次的那种
After a few days we did get to see a few images.
几天后 我们确实看到了一些图像
应该是高增益天线，公开资料也标注为定向天线
This is obviously from the top of the rover showing the solar panels unfurled the low gain antenna there
这张显然是从漫游车的顶部拍摄的 显示了太阳能电池板的展开 还有低增益天线的位置
and that circular feature there that's a thermal ballast.
还有那个圆形的特征 那是一个集热器
正十一烷
It contains a hydrocarbon in there
它含有一种碳氢化合物
which has a freezing point roughly around the temperature of Mars.
其熔点与火星(地表)的温度差不多
So it warms up during the day and cools down at night
所以它在白天升温 在晚上降温
but it tends to stay around that freezing point.
但倾向于保持在那个熔点附近
And then there was this monochrome image
然后是这张单色的图片
supplied by one of the hazard avoidance cameras on the rover itself
由火星车上的一个避障相机提供的
looking down the ramp onto the surface of Mars.
从坡道上看向火星表面
And it they took about a week to descend onto the surface
之后他们花了大约一个星期的时间让火星车下降到火星表面
and it wasn't just them waiting for the data to come back.
而这不仅仅是他们在等待数据的传回
They got the data.
他们得到了数据
They modeled the surface.
还对火星表面进行了建模
And then they actually built a simulated version in the lab
然后实际上在实验室里建立了一个模拟的版本
just to make sure that in the orientation that would go down the rails just fine.
只是为了确保在这个方向上 其可以顺利地沿着轨道前进
Apparently the suspension system used by Zhurong has some extra active components
显然 祝融所使用的悬挂系统有一些额外的活动部件
and they can raise the front and the rear of the rover independently if necessary.
而且可以在必要时分别提升车头和车尾
But yeah this is a really cool little animation showing the descent onto the surface
但是 这是一个非常酷的小动画 显示了下降到地面的过程
and of course we get to see the lander that it came down on.
当然 我们还可以看到其下降时所在的着陆器
And I think it's worth noting that
我认为值得注意的是
we haven't had a lander that's still being delivered to the surface of Mars like this
在此之前还没有像这样的着陆器被运送到火星的表面上
as in a rocket-powered platform with a ramp.
也就是一个有坡道的火箭动力平台
If you look at Curiosity and Perseverance, they use the sky crane
如果你看一下好奇号和毅力号 他们使用的是天空起重机
and Opportunity and Spirit had this big sort of bouncy ball thing.
而机遇号和勇气号使用的是大的弹跳球之类的东西
This is a single rocket engine landing on the surface of Mars
而这是一个使用单台火箭发动机在火星表面的着陆
and we'll talk a little more about that later.
而我们稍后会详细讨论这个问题
Now around the same time Tianwen-1 was able to return this image of the landing site.
那么大约在同一时间轨道器能够传回这个着陆点的图像
Now Tianwen-1 is very much a science satellite in its own right
那么轨道器在很大程度上是一颗科学卫星 对吧
and as it's working as a relay
由于它是作为一个中继站工作的
because it's had to set its orbit to synchronize with the rover
因为它不得不设置其轨道以与漫游车同步
it's sort of limiting its science gathering capabilities
这有点限制了它的科学收集能力
but anyway on the left this is before.
但无论如何 左边是着陆之前的情况
On the right this is after and you see three locations marked on Mars.
右边是着陆之后 你可以看到火星上有三个标记了的位置
At the top you have the lander showing an interesting burn pattern around it.
在顶部 你可以看到着陆器周围的一个有趣的燃烧图案
There's two objects there because one is the lander the other is the rover.
那里有两个物体 因为一个是着陆器 另一个是漫游车
Below that they have the aeroshell and the parachute marked.
在这下面的标记 则是气动背罩和降落伞着陆的位置
And to the southwest of that that is where the heat shield landed.
而在它的西南方 是防热大底着陆的地方
Of course NASA has its own imaging capabilities.
当然 NASA有自己的成像能力
It has the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter with the HiRISE camera
它有火星勘测轨道器的高分辨率成像科学设备
and that's able to get resolutions down to like half a meter or less.
其分辨率可达0.5米甚至更低
In this image you can very clearly see the lander and the rovers are two separate entities
在这张图片中 你可以非常清楚地看到着陆器和漫游车是两个独立的实体
and depending upon how you process this there's evidence of the ramps being visible.
而且根据你的处理方式 可以看到坡道存在的证据
On the right side of this image facing mostly east.
其在这张图片的右侧 主要面向东方
And yes the burn scar is a very interesting shape and I had a lot of questions about this.
是的 废气燃烧的痕迹是一个非常有趣的形状 我有很多关于这个的问题
It shows us a generally dark area with two light areas heading to the north and the south
它向我们展示了一个总体上偏暗的区域 有两个向北和向南偏亮的区域
and this is sort of very similar in some ways to what we saw for Perseverance's landing
这在某些方面与我们看到的毅力号着陆的情况非常相似
but that was via a sky crane.
但那是通过一个天空起重机实现的着陆
And its shape was due to having rockets that were firing over the top of the rover to the left and the right
而且它的形状是由于有火箭在漫游车的顶部向左和向右点火的缘故
and those formed two distinct burn marks
而这些形成了两个明显的燃烧痕迹
and then along the middle there was a stagnation zone where the air or the gases didn't flow quite as fast
然后沿着中间有一个停滞区 那里的空气或气体的流动速度不是很高
but Zhurong's lander only had a single engine
但是祝融的着陆器只有一台发动机
and from this image there was nothing getting in the way of the flow.
而从这个图像来看 没有任何东西妨碍了气体的流动
There were four legs but if the four legs were responsible for causing these two bright lobes
着陆器有四条腿 但如果是因为这四条腿造成了这两个偏亮区域的话
how did that work.
那是怎么做到的
Why didn't you see a cross-shaped pattern.
为什么图案不是十字形的
So I think what this is is a post-landing event.
所以我认为这是一个着陆后的事件
After they land they've got high-pressure propellant tanks
在他们着陆后 推进剂罐仍处在高压状态
and they just want to vent them.
而他们只是想把推进剂排放出来
And the vents just happen to be located out of the side.
而排放口恰好位于着陆器侧外位置
These are the sides that are 90 degrees away from the landing ramp
同时与下降坡道呈90度角
so they're not going to get in the way of that.
这样就不会妨碍到坡道
I think that's what's going on here.
我想这就是这里发生的事情
Also if you look at this image of the lander
另外 如果你看一下这个着陆器的图像
this is sort of lined up with the roll reaction control thrusters.
排出的气体方向似乎能与滚转反推力系统(RCS)对齐
So those are sitting along the edge
也就是那些放在着陆器边缘的发动机
and if you imagine when this is going down
而如果你想象一下 在它下降的时候
there is an aeroshell over the top of that and the heat shield underneath
这上面有一个气动背罩 下面有一个防热大底
and that's where the jets poke out through the aeroshell so that they can control the descent.
而这里就是喷射流穿过气动背罩的地方 这样就可以控制下降了
So it's conceivable that they just depressurize the system by firing those engines as well.
那么可以想象 他们只是通过点燃这些发动机来为系统减压
And those are pointed at 90 degrees to that ramp and exactly along the line of those burn scars.
而这些发动机与坡道成90度 正好能对上这些燃烧的痕迹
Also this image gives us an amazing view of the crater which was made underneath the lander
同时 这张图片提供了一个令人惊异的视角 即着陆器下方的坑洞
due to the rocket exhaust from that main engine softly touching down on Mars.
这是由于在火星软着陆时的主发动机产生的火箭废气而形成的
Now this is a much deeper crater than we've seen on other planetary landers
那么 比起其他行星着陆器在着陆过程中产生坑洞 这个更深
but really it's the first time we've seen underneath a Mars lander which has landed on a rocket.
但实际上 这是我们第一次看到使用火箭(发动机)着陆的火星着陆器下方的情况
For comparison the Chang'e missions to the moon
作为比较 登月的嫦娥系列任务
they didn't leave a crater that was nearly so obvious.
并没有留下如此明显的坑洞
And that's because they shut their engine down about 15 feet above the surface
那是因为他们在离地表5米的地方关闭了发动机
and then fell to the surface.
然后落到地面上
They didn't do that on Mars.
他们在火星上并没有这样做
They powered all the way to the surface.
火箭发动机一直点火 直到触地
But also there's a strong effect whereby a rocket in a vacuum expands out very quickly
但也归因于一个强烈的效应 即在真空中的废气很快就会膨胀出来
whereas a rocket in an atmosphere even an atmosphere as thin as that of Mars
而在大气层中的火箭 即使是像火星那样稀薄的大气层
will be collimated
都会被集中起来
and form into a jet that bores into the surface much more efficiently than it would on the moon.
并形成喷射流 比在月球上更有效地钻入表面
This is one of the things that leads to the sky crane
这也是天空起重机设计的原因之一
when you think about it sounds a bit ridiculous
当你想到(天空起重机的设计)时 听起来有点可笑
but when actually you look at the science it's the best way to do it.
但实际上 当你看到科学时 这是最好的实现方法
There's another little engineering feature here.
这里还有一个小小的工程特点
There's a little cylindrical object that sort of hangs out from underneath the lip there.
有一个小小的圆柱形物体 从着陆器边缘下面挂出来
That is like the black box that was there in case of an accident.
这差不多是一个黑匣子 以防有事故的发生
They had a team build this
他们有一个团队负责这个的建造
and you can get an idea how big it is by this photo of a guy working on it on the train.
你可以通过这张在火车上工作的人的照片来了解它有多大
They shot this out of a cannon to make sure it could survive any reasonable impact
他们用大炮把它打出来 以确保它能经受住任何合理的撞击
and that was there if there was a crash it would be able to transmit some parts of the telemetry
而且 如果发生碰撞 它将能够传输某些部分的遥测数据
so that they could perhaps have better chance next time.
以便进行改进 提高下次着陆的成功率
But yeah they didn't need it.
但是 是的 这次就不需要了
After a while they did also start sharing engineering camera views.
一段时间后 他们确实也开始分享工程相机的视图
This is of course parachute deployment
当然这是降落伞的部署
which NASA didn't really capture camera views of the parachute deployment until Perseverance.
而NASA在毅力号之前没有真正捕捉到降落伞部署的相机视图
And yeah I can see why. These days there's your cameras are so much cheaper
而且是的 我明白为什么 现在相机便宜多了
so it makes sense to capture this data and share it for improvements of future flights.
所以捕捉这些数据并分享给未来的飞行并进行改进是有意义的
This is the aeroshell getting popped off.
这是启动背罩被弹开的情况
You can see the parachute pulling it away.
你可以看到降落伞把它拉走了
And of course once this goes away the vehicle starts to go into power descent mode.
当然 一旦它离开 航天器就开始进入动力下降模式
Uses its rocket propulsion.
使用它的火箭推进器
It has many sensors. It has cameras, radar, other on-board image processing looking for a landing site.
它有许多传感器 它使用摄像头 雷达 以及其他机载图像处理装置来寻找着陆点
They chose the plain of Utopia Planitia
他们选择了乌托邦平原来着陆
because it was pretty well known to be an area with a lot of flat spaces.
因为众所周知 它是一个有很多平坦空间的地区
Therefore relatively easy to land on.
因此相对容易着陆
It's believed that Utopia Planitia used to be a sea at some point in the past.
据信 乌托邦平原在过去的某个时候曾经是一片海域
There's signs of an ancient shoreline at higher elevations
在高处有古代海岸线的迹象
so this was probably underwater in the past.
所以过去这里可能是在水下
And this image here actually gives you a really good idea of the sort of quality of the surface here.
那么这张图片实际上让你对这里的地表质量有一个非常好的了解
This is also one of the sort of great images from the mission as far as I'm concerned.
就我而言 这也是这次任务中最棒的图像之一
NASA hasn't done anything like this.
NASA还没有做过这样的事情
They had to carry an extra camera and then set it down on the surface of the planet
他们需要携带一个额外的相机 然后把它放在行星的表面上
so that it could take a photo of the rover and the lander together.
这样它就能拍到漫游车和着陆器的合影
And this is great PR.
而这是很好的公关
This is a country that's absolutely understanding the prestige
这样肯定能获得声望
that it can gain through communication of its spaceflight capabilities.
其他人可以借此得知中国的航天实力
And if you thought that dropping a camera on the surface of Mars to take a photo of your rover was cool.
而如果你认为在火星表面扔下一台相机来拍下漫游车是很酷的
Well they dropped a camera off in deep space so it could take a photograph of the spacecraft in flight.
那么 他们在深空扔下一个相机 以便拍摄航天器飞行时的照片 (感觉更酷)
Japan's Hayabusa 2 mission made extensive use of deployable cameras to get scientific imagery
日本的隼鸟2号任务广泛使用了可部署的相机来获得科学图像
but these amazing images are entirely there for their PR value.
但这些惊人的(自拍)图像完全是为了其公关价值
After the initial reconnaissance and photo opportunities, Zhurong headed off south
在最初的侦察和拍照机会之后 祝融号向南驶去
and I think its main target was this black object in the distance
而我认为它的主要目标是远处的这个黑色物体
which is the aeroshell and the parachute attached to it.
这就是气动背罩和连接在上面的降落伞
Again this is a mission which is doing science
同样 这也是一项正在进行的科学任务
but part of that science is figuring out how best to land on Mars
但这一科学的一部分是弄清楚如何更好地着陆火星
and inspecting your hardware can provide all sorts of extra information on that front.
而检查你的设备可以提供这方面的各种额外信息
And this stands in stark contrast to the more mature NASA program
而这与更成熟的NASA项目形成鲜明的对比
where the engineering data which might get gained from analyzing the parachute
在这种情况下 分析降落伞中可能获得的工程数据的科学价值
is outweighed by the fact that there's a small risk that the rover could get tangled in the parachute
与漫游车存在着很小的风险被降落伞缠住来说 不值一提
and lose the scientific value that the rover wants to bring from its analysis.
一旦被缠住 漫游车后续(漫游能力和对不同土壤成分)分析的科研价值都会丧失
But as of right now Zhurong has continued moving and has just completed one kilometer.
但就目前而言祝融号一直在继续移动 刚刚完成了一公里的距离
It's been moving about 10 meters per day.
它每天移动大约10米
Now the downsides of picking an easy place to land is that
那么 选择一个容易着陆的地方的坏处是
there's not actually much in the way of really interesting features that stand out.
实际上并没有什么真正突出而有趣的特征可供研究
Again this probably may well have been a sea floor in the past
同样的 这里在过去很可能是一个海床
but this is a mission that has got this ground penetrating radar which is looking down into the surface.
但这次任务配有次表层雷达的任务 可以向下看到地表内的结构
And we're not getting the data back from that just yet.
而我们现在还没有得到这个数据
There's a lot of analysis that has to go into that.
这个领域内肯定存在很多分析
But also Tianwen-1 is going to move to a new orbit soon
但是天问一号轨道器也将很快进入一个新的轨道
and it'll stop being able to continually service the rover.
而它将不再能够继续为漫游车提供服务
The rover has already exceeded its planned 90 days of operation
探测器已经超过了其计划的90天的运行时间
but I expect it will continue heading southwards possibly towards some distant peak
但我预计它将继续向南行驶 可能是朝向一些遥远的山峰
or some other structure that is geologically interesting.
或者其他一些具有地质意义的结构
And we'll see how far it gets.
而到时候我们会知道它能走多远
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]